Guide to the A. V. Williams Jackson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
A. V. Williams Jackson papers
1889-1909
MS 1009
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
Notes and drafts of A. V. Williams Jackson for articles and speeches, largely on Sanskrit and Avestan grammar and literature and the cultures of India and Iran. Also included is a program for the Joint Meetings of a Philological Societies of the United States (1894).
Jackson, A. V. Williams (Abraham Valentine Williams), 1862-1937
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1945.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of A. V. Williams Jackson, professor of Indo-Iranian languages at Columbia University (1895-1935), consist of notes and drafts for articles and speeches, many of which were subsequently published. The primary topics are Sanskrit and Avestan grammar and literature and the cultures of India and Iran. Several writings on Classical and western literature are also included. The final items in the collection are a program for the Joint Meetings of the Philological Societies of the United States (1894), with some related materials.
The writings are arranged in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
A. V. Williams Jackson was born in New York City, on February 9, 1862. For the majority of his life, Jackson was associated with Columbia University. He received an A.B. there in 1883, an A.M. the following year, an L.H.D. the year after that, and in 1886, a Ph.D. Between 1895 and 1935, he was a professor of Indo-Iranian languages at Columbia. He was the author of many books and travelled extensively in the Near East and South Asia. A. V. Williams Jackson died on August 8, 1937.
Avestan language; Iranian languages; Linguistics; Sanskrit language; India -- Civilization; Iran -- Civilization; Educators; Linguists; Jackson, A. V. Williams (Abraham Valentine Williams), 1862-1937
- Inventory
  - "Avesta Grammatical Jottings", 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Avestan Grammatical Notes", 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Avestan Etymologies", [1889] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Circle of Sovereignty in the Avesta", 1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Avesta ayohšusta and Miscellaneous Avestan Notes", 1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "A, the first letter in the English as in almost every known alphabet...", 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Notes on Zoroaster and the Zartusht Nāmah", 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Ahura Mazda", [1894] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Amesha Spentas", 1895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Dualism: The Kingdom of Good and the Kingdom of Evil", [1895] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "On the Date of Zoroaster", 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Notes on Some Persian Names in the Book of Esther", 1896 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Disguising in the Stage as a Dramatic Device in Sanskrit Plays", 1898 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Dyrus's Dream of the Winged Figure of Darius in Herodotus", [1899] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pahlavī Version of Vd. 18, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Phl. Aūtak ", Udak Vadhaşhana, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Khaiber Pass", [pre-1901] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "A Visit to Buddha's Footprint on Adam's Peak, Ceylon", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Hindu Yogis, Fakirs, or Ascetics", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Literature of India and Persia", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "A Glimpse into the Crater of Vesuvius", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "General Concept of the Amesha Spentas", undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Sketch of the Syntax", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Some Suggestions for Studying Shakspere", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Yasna", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Writings on syntax, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Program for the Joint Meeting of the Philological Societies of the United States, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 26)